<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Projects | Journal of a Ph. D.</title><link>https://journalofaphd.github.io/project/</link><atom:link href="https://journalofaphd.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Projects</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://journalofaphd.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Projects</title><link>https://journalofaphd.github.io/project/</link></image><item><title>Many-Body Perturbation Theory Calculations of Anatase TiO₂</title><link>https://journalofaphd.github.io/project/mbpt/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://journalofaphd.github.io/project/mbpt/</guid><description>&lt;p>The influence of non-interacting Kohn-Sham Hamiltonian on the non-self
consistent GW (G0 W0 ) quasiparticle gap and Bethe-Salpeter-Equation(BSE) optical
spectra of anatase TiO2 is systematically evaluated. G0 W0 and BSE calculations are
carried out starting with HSE06 (Heyd-Scuseria-Ernzerhof) type functionals containing
20, 25 and 30 % exact Hartree-Fock exchange. The results are also compared against
G0 W0 +BSE calculations starting from semi-local(PBE) functionals. Our results
indicate that the G0 W0 and BSE calculations of anatase TiO2 depend critically on
the mean-field starting point, wherein its dependence is mainly introduced through
the dielectric screening evaluated at the intermediate G0 W0 . We find that the band
dispersion, density of states, and consequently the oscillator strengths of optical
excitation and spatial localization of excitons are insensitive to the starting points
while the quasiparticle gap, optical gap and exciton binding energies are strongly
affected. G0 W0 quasiparticle gap of anatase TiO2 computed over hybrid functional
starting points is typically overestimated compared to measured values. However, by
varying the amount of exact exchange, the dielectric screening can be tuned, and thus
the quasiparticle gap. Exciton binding energy is shown to increase in proportion to
the increase of the amount of exact exchange. A simple extrapolation of the calculated
data leads to the exact match with the recently measured value with 13 % of the exact
exchange. Systematic analysis of G0 W0 +BSE calculation starting from screened hybrid
functionals provided in this study forms a reference for all such future calculations of
pristine anatase TiO2 and its derivatives.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Phtodynamic Therapy</title><link>https://journalofaphd.github.io/project/pdt/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://journalofaphd.github.io/project/pdt/</guid><description>&lt;p>Antimicrobial photodynamic therapy (aPDT) is an emerging strategy to treat antibiotic resistant micro-
organisms. This technique is selective, painless, less invasive, and can be focused on multiple targets, thereby ensuring photodestruction of target cells without producing photoresistant cells. The antimicrobial effect of this strategy relies on an oxidative burst that occurs when photoreactive
molecules are exposed to certain wavelengths of light. A nontoxic dye or photoreactive molecule
called a photosensitizer, light of suitable wavelength, and molecular oxygen are the three major compo nents involved in the photodynamic inactivation of microbial cells. Generation of
reactive oxygen species (ROS) plays a key role in aPDT. The excited photosensitizer, after illumination with a light of suitable wavelength, enters into an unstable triplet state resulting in ROS generation, which occurs through two different photoprocesses. In a type I photoreaction, electron transfer from the triplet state photosensitizer to the surrounding oxygen occurs and results in the formation of super-oxide, peroxide, and hydroxyl radicals. In a type II photoreaction, energy is transferred directly from the triplet state photosensitizer to molecular oxygen, thereby forming singlet oxygen which is highly reactive. ROS can act on a diverse range of cellular targets, causing death of a broad range of pathogens by damaging almost all biomolecules including lipids, protein, and nucleic acids&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Stokes-Mueller Polarimetry</title><link>https://journalofaphd.github.io/project/dsmp/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://journalofaphd.github.io/project/dsmp/</guid><description>&lt;p>We use the double Stokes–Mueller polarimetry (DSMP) technique, to characterize a large size (3x3x5 mm) Potassium titanyl phosphate (KTP) crystal. The crystal undergoes second harmonic generation with type II phase matching. The study of standard KTP crystal using the DSMP technique helps to validate the e±ciency of this technique. We were able to extract the crystal&amp;rsquo;s double Mueller matrix, relative contribution of the susceptibility tensor components, the phase di®erence between the susceptibility tensor components, etc. We could determine the crystal axes orientation using this optical technique,
which was not possible through a single crystal X-Ray di®raction technique for such a large size
crystal for which both optic axes and crystallographic axes are the same. Axes direction de-
termined from polarization microscope measurements and Laue di®raction measurements on
KTP crystal is compared with those obtained from DSMP measurements.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The schematic of DSMP performed on a KTP crystal to extract the nonlinear optical
properties of crystal is shown in the figure above. Here, we consider the propagation of light
along the Y -axis and the polarization of light in XZ-plane in the laboratory frame
coordinates. The experiment involves the generation of nine states of polarization
incident on the material using PSG. The material of study, the KTP crystal is type II phase-matched nonlinear crystal which has an orthorhombic crystal structure and is biaxial in nature. The phase-matched crystal produces second harmonic generated light whose state of polarization is determined by measuring its linear Stokes vector.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Time-Dependent Density Functional Theory</title><link>https://journalofaphd.github.io/project/tddft/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://journalofaphd.github.io/project/tddft/</guid><description>&lt;p>The field induced changes of the electronic structure affect the optical properties of the medium; the external force polarizes the material and induces oscillatory motion of the excited carriers. The oscillating dipoles emit a polarization wave which can modify temporal and spatial properties of the incident field. For sufficiently strong perturbing fields the polarization response of the medium becomes nonlinear. The nonlinear contribution to the polarization gives rise to a variety of nonlinear optical phenomena. This chapter discusses theoretical description of nonlinear optical pulse propagation in materials and experimental probes to investigate them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Laser-matter interaction dynamics involves the the excitation of the particle-hole pair. The particle and hole carriers affects the electromagnetic response of the material, screening the field depending on its density. These aspects of electron dynamics are included within the framework of time-dependent density functional theory (TDDFT). TDDFT is fully quantum mechanical and does not require any assumptions about the dynamics. The electronic motion within TDDFT is described by the time-dependent Kohn-Sham equation (TDKS) for the evolution of single particle orbitals (Kohn-Sham orbitals). TDKS can be viewed as an alternative formulation of time-dependent quantum mechanics but, in contrast to the normal approach that relies on wave-functions and on the many-body Schrödinger equation, its basic variable is the one-body electron density. From the density obtained by TDKS, we obtain the time-dependent polarizability p(t) of a system with a given external time-dependent potential. p(t) essentially contain all information of the system interacting with the external field. We apply TDDFT to describe the nonlinear weak-field and non-perturbatvie electron dynamics of TiO2 induced by intense ultrashort laser pulses.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>DFT simulation of anatase TiO₂</title><link>https://journalofaphd.github.io/project/dft/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://journalofaphd.github.io/project/dft/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The Superior optical and electronic properties of Titanium Dioxide makes it a promising candidate for designing multifunctional devices tailor-made to use for various applications. Optical properties, especially nonlinear optical properties, of Titanium dioxide changes significantly while it is doped with metals like Silver, Gold and Manganese. Rather than exhibiting a monotonous enhancement or diminution of nonlinear optical properties with respect to an increase in the concentration of the dopant it attains maximum at certain optimal concentrations. First principle simulation of optical properties of Titanium Dioxide, both pristine as well as doped with impurities at different concentrations will help us to predict the composition of the material with superior tailor-made properties before it is tested by experiments.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We carry out Ab-initio simulation of nonlinear optical properties of Titanium Dioxide based on Density Functional Theory(DFT). It is proposed to use different Hierarchy of approximations namely in DFT, Generalized Gradient Approximation(GGA), Hybrid DFT(HSE), to optimize the calculation parameters so that the results can be bench marked with experiments. In addition, in order to overcome the limitations of ground state DFT to calculate properties involving excited states (optical excitation spectra for instance) it requires the use of other computationally intensive advanced techniques that use Bethe-Salpeter Equation (BSE) or GW method. The proposed scheme of complete simulation involves&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Structural optimization(Volume Relaxation) of the system by energy minimization to optimize the structural parameters&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Self-Consistent Field Calculation of relaxed structure&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Calculation of Band structure and optical properties using HSE (Hybrid) Functional to account for the band gap problem inherent in standard GGA-DFT methods&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Quasi-particle Correction to band structure and optical properties of bulk anatase titanium dioxide by performing Hybrid DFT and Green’s function based GW calculations&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Repetition of the above for titanium dioxide system in which metal dopants are incorporated.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>We plan to use 5 metal atoms as dopant each of which will be incorporated in the system in five different concentrations making it a set of 25 different computational systems. The average time required per computational system for carrying out the work as mentioned in the proposal is given below showing the detailed break-up over individual jobs. These have been estimated based on the benchmark calculation performed using Vienna Ab-initio simulation Package(VASP) for a super cell containing 50 to 60 atoms.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>